All right, it's time to talk about the
transatlantic trade system and its
multitudinous effects. And if you're
anything like me, well, that sounds like
a party. So, if you're ready to get them
brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, now if you'll recall in the last
video, we talked about the development
of the British colonies in the Americas
and how in the beginning it was pretty
rough for all involved, including but
not limited to resorting to cannibalism
in order to survive. Is this Jerry? This
tastes like jerry. But later into the
17th century, nobody was eating anyone
else anymore because most of the
colonists had figured out how to survive
and thrive economically. And for that,
they could thank the growth of the
transatlantic trade or trade across the
Atlantic Ocean. Now, if you've ever
found yourself in a casual lunchroom
conversation about 17th century
transatlantic trade, and let's be
honest, who hasn't found themselves in
that delectible situation? Then you
probably have heard about the triangular
trade. Now, these trade routes roughly
formed a triangle, and they're a good
illustration of the way maritime trade
bound states together economically
across the vast stinking ocean. So, one
way the cycle of trade worked was that
New Englanders shipped rum to West
Africa and then that rum was traded for
enslaved laborers and then those
laborers were shipped across the Middle
Passage to be traded for sugarcane in
the West Indies. And that sugarcane got
shipped right up to New England where it
could be distilled into rum and around
the triangle we go again. And I'm not as
concerned that you remember all the
goods that were traded. Although it
probably wouldn't hurt you to find an
empty brain fold and stuff it in there.
I'm more concerned that you understand
how dependent each economy had become on
goods from the other economies. I mean,
that rum isn't getting made without
sugarcane, and that sugarcane isn't
getting grown without enslaved labor.
And those enslaved laborers aren't
getting purchased without some rum in
the slave trader tongue. You smelling
what I'm stepping in here? I hope so,
because as the system grew more and more
profitable, it fundamentally shaped the
nature of colonial economies. And I'm
not talking only about the triangular
trade now, but all the various economic
dependencies that developed via trade
routes. And there are two major effects
of that that you should know. First, the
main priority of colonial economies was
to produce goods that were in high
demand along the trade routes and in
some cases to focus nearly their entire
economy on the production of high demand
commodities. And speaking of high demand
commodities, I reckon you're itching for
an A in your class and a five on your
exam in May. Now, if that's you, you
might want to check out my A Push
Heimler review guide, which is the
fastest and most complete way to study.
It's got exclusive unit review videos
that are not here on YouTube. It's got
practice questions, practice exams, and
note guides to follow along. It's also
got answer keys for every dang bit of
it. So get that clicky finger out and
check the link in the description.
Anyway, probably the best example of
colonial economy shaped by high demand
commodities is the production of
sugarcane in the British West Indies.
Now, it was Christopher Columbus himself
that introduced sugarcane to the
Caribbean. And once it was discovered
that the good soil and warm climate
could facilitate long growing seasons,
sugar cultivation began to dominate
colonial economies in places like
Barbados and Jamaica. And once Europeans
got more and more access to sugar, the
demand for it went hog wild. And it's
not hard to understand why. You drinking
nasty black coffee,
>> sweet yourself. Are you taking medicine
that tastes like an old monkeykey's
armpit?
>> Sweet yourself.
>> There were so many nasty tasting things
that could be made tasty with only a
little bit of sugar. And so, as demand
for sugar increased, the economies of
those sugar- producing islands became
almost entirely devoted to its
production. And so, the second and
related effect of this demand for sugar
was a massive increase in the demand for
enslaved laborers to do the intensive
work of planting and harvesting. In
large part, this demand was satisfied by
enslaved Africans. But often overlooked
was the large-scale enslavement of
American Indians to provide labor as
well. And because the working conditions
were so harsh and unforgiving, many
laborers died. And that only further
increased the demand for enslaved labor.
And so again, you can begin to see the
tight web of economic interdependence
being woven between the various states
across the Atlantic Ocean. Okay, now you
didn't think all this transatlantic
economic interdependence happened
without an economic ideology that
dictated the terms of its expansion. Did
you don't be crazy? No, it was in fact
the economic system known as
mercantalism that created the conditions
for everything I've been talking about.
Now by definition mercantalism was an
economic system that emphasized a
favorable balance of trade which is to
say greater exports than imports. And if
that doesn't make any sense to you then
as I am want to do allow me to compare
mercantalism to a pie and I think that's
going to help you understand how it all
fits together. So a pie as you know only
has so much pie and you can only slice
it into so many pieces and if one person
wants a bigger slice of that pie then
that means that other people are going
to get less. And to put it mildly
European economies during this period
loved them some pie. So mercantalist
states measured their own wealth in
terms of gold and silver. That was their
pie. And so there was only so much gold
and silver in the world. And so their
goal was to get as big a piece of that
pie as they could. So that's why
merkantalist states wanted to export
more goods than they import it. Because
when they export, gold comes in. But
when they import, gold goes out. Now, I
know we're all having a blast talking
about mercantalism in its theoretical
form, but here's why it's important. In
the mercantalist system, the whole
purpose of establishing colonies was to
enrich the mother state. In other words,
the whole job of the colony was to help
Big Mama get some more pie. And that's
where we start running into problems
with Big Mama Britain and her American
colonies. Now, remember that I mentioned
in a previous video that Britain's
American colonies developed systems that
allowed them to operate somewhat
independently of Great Britain property.
And that was kind of a necessity owing
to this big honking ocean that separated
them. But there came a time when Great
Britain, that sassy mercantalist state,
attempted to clamp down on those
American colonies and force them to
serve the imperial economy. And perhaps
the most notorious example of this
effort came in the form of the
Navigation Act, which basically imposed
three rules. First, any goods that the
colonist imported had to first pass
through ports in England in order to be
taxed. Second, any goods that colonist
traded had to be transported on English
ships. And third, the British produced a
list of highly valuable colonial goods
that could only be exported to England.
So, this legislation had the effect of
stripping the American colonists of
their autonomy and making economic
decisions that best served them.
Instead, their economies were now made
to serve Great Britain alone. And that
was a bad deal for those colonists who
had been used to acting independently.
However, it wasn't long before the
colonists remembered that big honking
ocean separating them from Great
Britain. And they soon found that in a
lot of cases, they could ignore the
navigation acts without punishment. And
this is what we call salutary neglect.
And to be clear, salutary neglect wasn't
like a formal policy or anything. It
just kind of happened on account of
Great Britain being distracted by other
more pressing issues elsewhere and
therefore did not enforce their colonial
laws consistently. But that neglect was
somewhat intermittent. And so there were
times when Britain worked harder to
control its American colonies by
removing their autonomy. For example,
starting in 1686, King James II created
the Dominion of New England, which was a
kind of super colony that combined all
these colonies up here. And in this
super colony, the king appointed a
governor who didn't have to answer to
the colonial elected assemblies. And
that governor in turn appointed local
officials to replace elected officials.
Now, this arrangement of course made it
much easier for the crown to have
tighter control over colonial policies
and trade enforcement. However, in 1688,
an event known as the Glorious
Revolution occurred in England in which
Parliament overthrew King James and
reestablished their own governmental
power. And in doing so, they installed
new monarchs, William and Mary, who
agreed to rule in accordance with the
increased power of Parliament. And when
news of that revolution reached the
American colonies, rebellions broke out.
The most significant effect of which was
the collapse of the dominion of New
England and the return of elected
colonial assemblies. Okay. Now, most of
what I've been focusing on here is
European trade with their colonial
empires. However, let's not forget that
colonial people were still trading with
various American Indian groups as well.
And that had three significant effects
you're going to need to remember. First,
colonists introduced European goods to
indigenous people, most notably metal
tools and firearms and horses. And for
those indigenous groups that received
guns, for example, the power dynamics
between them and rival indigenous groups
shifted significantly in the favor of
those with the boomsticks. Second, trade
with American Indians led to the spread
of epidemic diseases like smallox and
measles, which, as we covered in
previous videos, led to devastation
among indigenous populations. And third,
as indigenous people grew more and more
dependent on European goods, they became
more vulnerable to manipulation and
internal division. Now, a good example
of the interaction between Great
Britain's mercandalist policies and
conflicts with American Indians is
Bacon's Rebellion. Now, we're going to
talk a lot more about this in another
video, namely about the relationship
between this rebellion and the
transition to reliance on African
slavery in the colonies. But for now,
all you really need to know is that a
group of poor and disenfranchised
indentured servants began attacking
American Indian groups on the frontier
of Virginia, at least one of which was
an ally of the British. The rebels then
turned to attack the governor, William
Berkeley, who fled from his attackers.
However, Berkeley was able to secure
reinforcements from the British Navy and
eventually put down the rebellion. Now,
afterward, the colony came under much
more direct control of the crown for a
time because if a colony is busy
suppressing rebellions, then they're not
exporting tobacco and serving their
purpose in the larger mercantalist party
of the empire. But after the Glorious
Revolution and the mounting expenses of
continually getting involved with
managing colonial disputes, Parliament
began to loosen its grip on some of
those policies that aimed to tighten
control over their colony. And so
conflicts like this with American
Indians sometimes led to efforts to
tighten control and sometimes control
was loosened either because of cost or
commitments to other more pressing
matters. The point is enforcement of
these mercantalist policies was erratic.
Okay, you can click here to watch my
other videos covering unit 2 and you can
click here to grab my A push him review
guide which will help you study as fast
as possible. Now I appreciate you coming
around and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. He la.